{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This woman nearly fell over during a botched curtsy in front of King George VI. This woman was sent to Craig House in 1941 and was later relocated to St. Coletta School for Exceptional Children, where she spent the last 66 years of her life. Eunice Shriver founded the Special Olympics in honor of this woman, who underwent a failed lobotomy 22 years before the assassination of her brother John. For ten points, name this member of the Kennedy family.",
      "answer": "Rosemary Kennedy or Rose Marie Kennedy"
    },
    {
      "question": "This empire was founded by As-Saffah shortly after a military victory at the Zab River. Under Al-Mansur, this empire sent four thousand mercenaries to help put down the An Lushan Rebellion. This empire ceded power to the Seljuks in the 11th century and was eventually destroyed by Hulagu Khan’s Mongol armies. Harun al-Rashid, a ruler of this empire, established the House of Wisdom in its capital of Baghdad. For ten points, name this successor to the Umayyad Caliphate that oversaw the Islamic Golden Age.",
      "answer": "Abbasid Caliphate"
    },
    {
      "question": "One side’s strategy in this event was later replicated in Operations Ariel and Cycle, which targeted Le Havre and Cherbourg. In anticipation of this event, 26 May was declared a national day of prayer by George VI. Codenamed Operation Dynamo, this event’s success relied upon “little ships” such as yachts and civilian fishing boats that crossed the English Channel. For ten points, identify this “miracle” in which the British Expeditionary Force was evacuated from a French beach.",
      "answer": [
        "evacuation from Dunkirk",
        "descriptive answers that mention Dunkirk"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Gaspar Gorricio helped this man compile the Book of Prophecies. While traveling with the Pinz´on brothers, this man encountered the chief Guacanagari. This subject of the Capitulations of Santa Fe was replaced by Francisco de Bobadilla as governor of the Indies. The 400th anniversary of his most notable achievement was commemorated by the 1893 Chicago World’s Fair. For ten points, name this Genoan-born explorer who commanded the Nin˜a, the Pinta, and the Santa Maria to the New World.",
      "answer": [
        "Christopher Columbus or Cristofor Colombo",
        "or Crist´obal Col´on"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "While working for this government, an orphaned radio specialist aids in the hunt for the Sea of Flame jewel in Anthony Doerr’s Pulitzer-winning novel All the Light We Cannot See. Annemarie Johansen fools a canine unit employed by this government using a basket laced with cocaine in a novel in which a group of refugees flee to Sweden from this government’s reach. For ten points, Lois Lowry’s novel Number the Stars is set during what government’s occupation of Denmark in 1943?",
      "answer": [
        "Nazi Germany",
        "either underlined portion",
        "the Third Reich"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was granted foreign aid from France through the Treaty of Barwalde. This man invaded Livonia in his early career to fend off a challenge from his Polish cousin Sigismund III, and his country was administered by Axel Oxenstierna after this man was slain leading a cavalry charge at Lu¨tzen. This man had earlier secured a decisive victory against the Holy Roman Empire at Breitenfeld. For ten points, name this Lion of the North who led Sweden in the Thirty Years War.",
      "answer": "Gustavus Adolphus or Gustav II Adolf"
    },
    {
      "question": "A cartoonish video game based on this board game includes a faction of cats led by Generalissimo Meow. In 1957, filmmaker Albert Lamorisse invented this boardgame, whose 1999 Napoleon-themed edition added fortresses. Italy and Spain are among the neutral zones in the “Castle” edition of this board game. Players can roll up to three red dice to start an attack in this game. The Australia strategy may be employed in, for ten points, what strategic board game whose board contains 42 territories spread out across six continents?",
      "answer": [
        "Risk",
        "Risk: Factions"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man led a military action that freed Lewis Washington from being a hostage in the Allstadt House and Ordinary, property that had been owned by this man’s family. This colonel ordered Israel Greene to attack an engine house after his aide-de-camp, Jeb Stuart, failed to negotiate a peaceful departure from a federal armory. For ten points, name this man who led forces against John Brown at Harpers Ferry in 1859, years before he served as the commander of the Confederate Army.",
      "answer": "Robert Edward Lee"
    },
    {
      "question": "Robert Salmond first applied this policy in ordering Colonel Seton to man the pumps during an event memorialized in Rudyard Kipling’s poem “Soldier an’ Sailor Too.” This phrase was popularized after that incident in which the troopship Birkenhead struck a rock just off the Western Cape in South Africa. J. Bruce Ismay was criticized for not following this code, which explained why several partially filled lifeboats were set off from the Titanic. For ten points, name this unofficial, chivalric policy that prioritizes certain passengers during shipwrecks.",
      "answer": [
        "women and children are saved from a shipwreck first",
        "descriptive equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Hegedu¨s Reforms attempted to combat the effects of this phenomenon as Hungary faced it in the aftermath of the Treaty of Trianon. Another instance of this phenomenon was sparked by a general strike in the Ruhr. J.P. Morgan Jr. co-led a conference that sought a solution to that instance of this phenomenon, in which the Reichsbank produced notes worth 100 trillion marks. For ten points, name this type of destabilization of the value of a currency, famously experienced by the Weimar [vye-mar] Republic.",
      "answer": "hyperinflation"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was advised in his waning years by a group known as the Rolex 12, and he previously suppressed a wave of student protests called the First Quarter Storm. This leader, who attempted to create a “New Society” in the model of Suharto, ordered the assassination of a political rival in an airport in 1983; that rival’s wife, Corazon, succeeded this man after he was toppled in the 1986 People Power Revolution. For ten points, name this corrupt former Philippine president whose wife Imelda owned a famous shoe collection.",
        "answer": "Ferdinand Marcos"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This is the surname of Benigno, the rival politician who Marcos ordered assassinated in 1983, and Corazon, his wife who ruled the Philippines for six years after Marcos was toppled.",
        "answer": "Aquino"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Before the recognition of these objects as important artifacts in 1899, many of them were ground into dust and used as a cure for malaria. A sixty day cycle using the Heavenly Stems and Earthly Branches was used to record data from these objects. Heated metal rods were used to crack these objects, on which questions were written. For ten points, name these objects that were used as divination tools used by Shang dynasty oracles whose common examples included ox scapulas.",
        "answer": [
          "oracle bones",
          "turtle shells",
          "ox scapula before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "On the subject of more successful malaria treatments, Tu Youyou won a 2015 Nobel Prize for her study on Chinese herbal treatments using a wormwood plant named in part for this Greek goddess of the wilderness.",
        "answer": [
          "Artemis",
          "Artemisia",
          "artemisinins"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ronald Ridenhour exposed this event in a damning letter to Congress, while Seymour Hersh was the first reporter to break this story. Ernest Medina was told to kill everything “walking, crawling, or growling” during this event, which was mitigated by interventions from Hugh Thompson’s helicopter crew. This war crime was carried out by Charlie Company in the hamlets surrounding Son My [son mee]. For ten points, name this 1968 massacre carried out by the US Army during the Vietnam War.",
        "answer": [
          "My Lai massacre",
          "Pinkville massacre",
          "Son My massacre before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This lieutenant, the leader of Charlie Company, was the only soldier convicted for his role in the massacre.",
        "answer": "William Laws Calley Jr."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Three works of art from this country appear in the background of a painting of the art supplier P`ere Tanguy [“pear” tan-ghee]. A work from this country showing plum branches was copied in an oil painting that added an orange border with nonsensical characters. A wood-based art form from this country was introduced to van Gogh and other European artists after trade with the Dutch was opened on the artificial island of Dejima. For ten points, name this home country of the artists Hiroshige and Hokusai, who painted Thirty-Six Views of Mount Fuji.",
        "answer": [
          "Japan",
          "Nippon"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This art form was used by Hokusai for his 36 Views of Mount Fuji and inspired countless European artists in the Japonisme movement. Its name translates to “pictures of the floating world.”",
        "answer": "ukiyo-e"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "When this man’s son vomited his poison, his assassins hired the wrestler Narcissus to strangle him in the bath, leading to the ascent of Pertinax. A book by this man partly written in Carnuntum tells the reader to “not then consider life a thing of any value” and may have been inspired by the works of Epictetus. This father of Commodus ruled alongside Lucius Verus in the second century AD. For ten points, name this last member of the Five Good Emperors and author of the Meditations.",
        "answer": "Marcus Aurelius Antoninus Augustus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marcus Aurelius succeeded this Roman emperor, his adoptive father. This husband of Faustina the Elder died at age 75 from a fever possibly brought on by bad cheese.",
        "answer": "Antoninus Pius or Titus Aurelius Fulvius Boionius Arrius Antoninus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Royal Dutch Shell was sued by people from this country after Ogoniland protesters, including Ken Saro-Wiwa and the Ogoni 9, were killed. In 2009, a group in this country besieged a Bauchi police station, instigating clashes that killed its leader Mohammed Yusuf; that group’s current leader, Abubakar Shekau, rebranded that group as the Islamic State in West Africa after pledging allegiance to ISIS. In 2014, over 200 schoolgirls were kidnapped in Chibok in, for ten points, what African country where Boko Haram bombed the UN building in Abuja in 2011?",
        "answer": "Nigeria"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2015, this rival of Olusegun Obasanjo became the first sitting Nigerian President to lose an election. This leader drew criticism for attending his niece’s wedding just after Boko Haram committed the Baga Massacre.",
        "answer": "Goodluck Jonathan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Porteous Riots occurred after the death of an ally of this man, Queen Caroline. This man put forth the requirement that all plays were to be reviewed by the Lord Chamberlain, probably because he disliked his caricaturization as Mr. Peachum in John Gay’s The Beggar’s Opera. This man was forced to resign from the Parliament after losing the War of Jenkins’ Ear. For ten points, name this man, usually considered the first Prime Minister of Great Britain.",
        "answer": [
          "Sir Robert Walpole, First Earl of Orford",
          "either",
          "both names"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Walpole made his fortune by wisely getting out at the top of this financial event, then came to power in the wake of its collapse and creating a sinking fund to reduce England’s national debt.",
        "answer": [
          "South Sea Bubble",
          "anything do to with the South Sea Company’s rise and/or fall"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this President’s administration, Southern senators limited federal use of domestic troops via the Posse Comitatus Act. A department in Paraguay is named for this President, who awarded Gran Chaco to Paraguay after the War of the Triple Alliance. This President promised to pull federal troops from the South to win an election after he lost the popular vote to Samuel Tilden. For ten points, name this man whose Presidency was assured by the Compromise of 1877.",
        "answer": "Rutherford B. Hayes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the Election of 1876, the electoral votes in Florida, Louisiana, and South Carolina were disputed by both parties, while the final, deciding vote came from this western state, where an elector was declared illegal.",
        "answer": "Oregon"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The New Deal",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Government retirement disability benefits program created in 1935 that issues nine-digit cards.",
          "answer": "Social Security Administration or SSA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Largest New Deal project, which employed millions of people to build public buildings and roads.",
          "answer": "Works Progress Administration or Work Projects Administration"
        },
        {
          "question": "Program that employed young men to plant trees and preserve the environment.",
          "answer": "Civilian Conservation Corps"
        },
        {
          "question": "Independent agency created to adjudicate union bargaining and unfair labor practices.",
          "answer": "National Labor Relations Board"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secretary of Labor under FDR, the first woman in the Cabinet.",
          "answer": "Francis Perkins"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorful animal symbol used to show compliance with the NIRA.",
          "answer": "Blue Eagle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Court case, known as the “sick chicken case,” that ruled the NIRA unconstitutional.",
          "answer": "A.L.A. Schechter Poultry Corp. v. United States"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Court case that found the Agricultural Adjustment Act unconstitutional.",
          "answer": "United States. v. Butler"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Medieval Russia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "16th century Russian Tsar famous for killing and torturing many of his subjects, including his own son and heir.",
          "answer": [
            "Ivan the Terrible",
            "Ivan IV Vasilyevich",
            "Ivan Grozny",
            "synonyms for Terrible, like Awesome"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty which ruled Russia for over 300 years, starting with Mikhail I in 1613.",
          "answer": "Romanov dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian Grand Prince who led his republic to victory at the Battle on the Ice in 1242.",
          "answer": "Alexander Nevsky"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mongol khanate which terrorized Russia in the 13th and 14th centuries with repeated invasions.",
          "answer": "Golden Horde"
        },
        {
          "question": "Grand Prince of Kiev from 980 to 1015 who converted to Christianity and later Christianized all of Kievan Rus’.",
          "answer": [
            "Vladimir the Great Sviatoslavich",
            "Vladimir I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Tyrannical secret police that attempted to suppress opposition to the Tsar by terrorizing civilians.",
          "answer": "oprichnina or oprichniki"
        },
        {
          "question": "Princely state of Kievan Rus’, the capital of its namesake republic and major rival of Muscovy.",
          "answer": "Novgorod"
        },
        {
          "question": "17th century Patriarch of Moscow who introduced many Church reforms, eventually leading to a schism in the Russian Orthodox Church.",
          "answer": "Patriarch Nikon"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "History of Australia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Precious metal extracted by the miners who led the Eureka Stockade uprising.",
          "answer": "gold"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for the indigenous peoples of Australia, 30 of whom were killed in the Myall Creek Massacre.",
          "answer": [
            "Aboriginal Peoples",
            "Australian Aborigines"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Body of water where James Cook first landed in Australia, which he named for its abundance of plants.",
          "answer": "Botany Bay"
        },
        {
          "question": "European country that sponsored Abel Tasman’s trip to Australia, in which he named Tasmania after Anthony van Diemen.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of the Seven United Netherlands",
            "the Dutch Republic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "State, once governed by William Bligh, where the British First Fleet settled the land around Sydney.",
          "answer": "New South Wales"
        },
        {
          "question": "Australian bushranger and outlaw who was captured and hung after a final gun battle with police at Glenrowan.",
          "answer": "Ned Kelly"
        },
        {
          "question": "British explorer who wrote A Voyage to Terra Australis and was the first to circumnavigate the continent.",
          "answer": "Matthew Flinders"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prolonged war launched by George Arthur in which British colonists drove out the indigenous peoples of Tasmania.",
          "answer": "Black War"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The third movement of this piece includes an unusual solo for the fourth horn player, and another section features the cellos and basses dismissing melodies from earlier movements. One of this piece’s melodies was adapted for the (20 pts)",
        "anthem of both the unrecognized state of Rhodesia and of the European Union. This piece’s final movement, dubbed a (10 pts)",
        "“symphony-within-a-symphony,” features the lyric “O friends, not these tones!” and adapted a Friedrich Schiller poem, “Ode to Joy.” For ten points, name this final symphony by Ludwig van Beethoven."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ludwig van Beethoven’s Symphony #9 in D minor, opus 125 or “Choral” Symphony",
        "“Symphony” and “Beethoven” are not necessary after each is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) As a lieutenant-colonel, this man led a bayonet charge on the left flank during the Battle of Mallavelly before failing in his first attack on Seringapatam in the Anglo-Mysore War. This resident of Apsley House threatened to (20 pts)",
        "resign if the Catholic Relief Act of 1829 was not passed; that unpopular decision that may have contributed to his nickname of (10 pts)",
        "“Iron Duke.” In another battle, this man famously said that either “night or the Prussians must come;” Blu¨cher’s Prussians did. For ten points, name this English general who defeated Napoleon at Waterloo."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Arthur Wellesley, first Duke of Wellington",
        "either"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) For supplying this leader with raw materials, Franz van Anraat was sentenced to seventeen years in prison. President of Zambia Kenneth Kaunda sent this leader a Boeing 747 filled with luxurious goods as a gift. Despite his country signing the (20 pts)",
        "Algiers agreement six years earlier, this leader launched an eight year-long war to gain control of the Shatt Al-Arab. This leader also launched the (10 pts)",
        "Al-Anfal campaign, which included the gassing of Kurds at Halabja. For ten points, name this Ba’athist leader of Iraq who was ousted in a US invasion in 2003."
      ],
      "answer": "Saddam Hussein"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This company’s questionable business tactics were revealed in the Halloween documents. This company managed to avoid paying any royalty fees to Spyglass by giving one of their products away for free. The CEO of this company was said to be (20 pts)",
        "“evasive and unresponsive” during a deposition in which he repeatedly said “I don’t recall.” Thomas Penfield Jackson ordered the (10 pts)",
        "breakup of this company in 1999, a ruling that was later reversed and settled. For ten points, name this company that was sued by the US government for monopolizing the computer industry by bundling Internet Explorer with the Windows operating system."
      ],
      "answer": "Microsoft Corporation"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ruler of this group named Reccared I converted to Christianity. The Suebi Kingdom was conquered and annexed by these people. The Muslim conquest of these people began after the Battle of Guadelete, where King (20 pts)",
        "Roderic was killed. The Reconquista began under Pelagius, a leader of this group, which had earlier defeated (10 pts)",
        "Rome at the Battle of Adrianople. The Roman province of Hispania was home to the kingdom of these people, who established a capital at Toledo. For ten points, name this eastern Gothic group, led by Alaric, that conquered modern-day Spain."
      ],
      "answer": "Visigoths"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man ordered Gideon Pillow to fix official reports that gave Pillow too much credit for this man’s victories. This man negotiated with James Douglas after a bloodless war over the San Juan Islands, the (20 pts)",
        "Pig War. This man headed the US Navy’s intimidation of South Carolina during the Nullification Crisis. This general, who led the first large-scale American (10 pts)",
        "amphibious attack in 1847, proposed blockading the Confederacy in the Anaconda Plan. For ten points, name this victor at Veracruz, a general nicknamed “Old Fuss and Feathers.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Winfield Scott"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This location was the site of a massive gold shield until it was looted by the Jat people. Lapis lazuli from the walls of this location was looted by British regulars, though Lord (20 pts)",
        "Curzon later ordered the restoration of this building. The Mahtab Bagh was discovered near this building, giving rise to a myth that it was supposed to be adjacent to a twin building made of (10 pts)",
        "black stone. A raised reflecting pool sits in front of this location, which was designed as a burial place for Mumtaz. For ten points, name this white marble mausoleum commissioned by Shah Jahan of India."
      ],
      "answer": "Taj Mahal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a battle during this war, Marguerite Higgins photographed Baldomero L´opez scaling a seawall before his death. Human wave tactics were used during this war’s Battle of Heartbreak (20 pts)",
        "Ridge. During this war, American forces were trapped at the Chosin Reservoir and F-86 Sabres fought in (10 pts)",
        "“MiG Alley.” Douglas MacArthur was relieved by President Truman during, for ten points, what 1950s war that ended with a demilitarized zone being established on an East Asian peninsula?"
      ],
      "answer": "Korean War"
    }
  ]
}